Guide to the W. Somerset Maugham Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
W. Somerset Maugham collection
1897-1956
GEN MSS 263
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.8
(5 boxes)
Contains letters from Maugham to various people, including William Morris Colles, Ada Leverson, Charles Hanson Towne, and Donald Goddard Wing; manuscript and proof versions of writings by Maugham, including "Ashenden, or the British agent", "Lady Frederick", and "On a Chinese Screen"; and an etching of Hugh Walpole hitting Elinor Mordaunt in the jaw.
Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1874-1965
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to W. Somerset Maugham, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection.
Authors, English -- Archives; Ashenden, or, the British agent; Lady Frederick: a comedy in three acts; On a Chinese screen; Colles, William Morris, 1855-1926; Leverson, Ada, 1862-1933; Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1874-1965; Mordaunt, Elinor, 1877?-1942; Towne, Charles Hanson, 1877-1949; Walpole, Hugh, 1884-1941; Wing, Donald Goddard, 1904-1972
- Letters from W. Somerset Maugham, 1947-56, n.d.; Series I
  - 45 Letters and cards to Lady Marion Bateman, 1947-56, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Scope and Contents
    Accompanied by one photograph and one clipping. Gift, 1971.
  - ALS to Ruth Buddington, Villa Mauresque, Cap. Ferrat, [1935] Sep 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    With envelope. Accompanied by carbon copy of TL from Ruth L. Buddington (later Ruth B. Leighton] to Maugham, 1935 Aug 24. Gift, 1963.
  - 3 ALS and 1 ANS to W. Morris Colles, 1899-1905 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gift, 1939.
  - ALS to [William Morris] Colles, Westminster, [1903 Nov 9] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Gift, 1947.
  - ALS to F. Tennyson Jesse, St. Jean Cap Ferrat, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Gift, 1977.
  - 38 ALS and 1 APS to Mrs. Ada Leverson, 1908-11, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
    Gift, 1955.
  - ALS to [Benjamin Moore-Fine], Villa Mauresque, Cap Ferrat, Mar 29 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Purchase, 1962.
  - 2 TLS to Miss Morse of the George H. Doran Company of New York, 1916, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 2 TLS to [John W.] Rumsey, the first with an autograph note at the end, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 4 ALS and 7 TLS to John W. Rumsey, various places, 1925-27, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - TLS to "Charlie" [Charles Hanson Towne], Bryanston Square, [London], 1924 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 10 TLS to Charles Hanson Towne; also 7 ALS with a typescript of each letter, various places, 1925-26, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - TLS to Mr. Wilensky, Villa Mauresque, Cap Ferrat, Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - ALS to Donald G. Wing, San Francisco, [1945] Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Gift, 1945.
  - TLS to Donald Goddard Wing, St. Jean-Cap Ferrat, 1954 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    With envelope. Gift, 1954.
  - TLS to Donald Goddard Wing, St. Jean-Cap Ferrat, 1954 Oct 22 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    This letter refers to his manuscript of "On a Chinese Screen," which he gave to the Yale Library in 1954. Gift, 1954.
- Writings of W. Somerset Maugham, 1928; Series II
  - "Ashenden", 1928 (Box 2, Folder 21-24)
    Typescript with a few autograph manuscript suggestions. Gift, 1951.
  - "The Extraordinary Sex," proof, signed, 1929 Mar 21
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 41
  - "Four Dutchmen," proof, signed, 1928 Nov 29
    See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 42
  - "In Hiding," proof, signed, 1929 Feb 23
    See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 43
  - "Lady Frederick", New York, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25-27)
    A play in typescript. An acting copy. 3 acts. Gift, 1958.
  - "The Man Who Made His Mark," proof, signed, 1929 May 30
    See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 44
  - "Mrs. Dot," New York, 1909 Aug 24 (Box 2, Folder 28-33)
    A play in typescript. Two acting copies. Gift, 1958.
  - "On a Chinese Screen," London, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Autograph manuscript. Several pages written on both sides. Bound in purple leather. Gift, 1954.
  - "Straight Flush," proof, signed, n.d.
    See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 45
  - "Strictly Personal", [1941] (Box 3, Folder 35-36)
    Autograph manuscript, with many autograph corrections and deletions. Accompanied by a TLS to Mr. Knollenberg, 1942 Sep 28, New York. Gift, 1942.
- Other, Series III
  Royalty agreements
  - For "The Explorer." Between Maugham and Lewis Waller of the Lyric Theatre, London, 1907 May 24 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - For "Eliza of Lambeth." Between Maugham and Thomas Fisher Unwin of London, 1897 Apr 6 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - For "The Making of a Saint." Between Maugham and Thomas Fisher Unwin of London, 1898 Apr 4 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - For "The Merry-Go-Round." Between Maugham and the firm of William Heinemann of London, 1904 Apr 6 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Artwork
    - Dyson, William Henry. Etching of Hugh Walpole hitting Eleanor Mordaunt in the jaw, n.d.
      Entitled "The manly art of self-defence or "Now no one can say that Maugham meant it for me!" Gift, 1959.
      See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 46
- Oversize, 1929 Mar 21
  - "The Extraordinary Sex," proof, signed (in Series II), 1929 Mar 21 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - "Four Dutchmen," proof, signed (in Series II), 1928 Nov 29 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - "In Hiding," proof, signed (in Series II) (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - "The Man Who Made His Mark," proof, signed (in Series II), 1929 May 30 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - "Straight Flush," proof, signed (in Series II), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Dyson, William Henry. Etching of Hugh Walpole hitting Eleanor Mordaunt in the jaw (in Series III), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 46)
- Additions Since June 1997, Series IV
  - MAUGHAM, W. SOMERSET
    - "Introduction" to Moll Flanders by Daniel Defoe (Box 6, Folder 47)
      1 item (8 leaves); 28 cm. Holograph, corrected. Purchase, 1997.